Guide to the Frederic Cole Smedley Collection 1914-1950 (Bulk 1934-1946) MS 022 MS 022
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Frederic Cole Smedley Collection
Bulk, 1934-1946
1914-1950, (Bulk 1934-1946)
MS 022
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
1.5 Linear feet
Smedley was an active member of the Socialist Party in the 1930s. He ran for Comptroller of Waterbury, CT on the Socialist platform in the municipal election of 1939 and in 1948 he was the Socialist Party candidate for U.S. Senator from Connecticut. Smedley was also an attorney for numerous labor and advocacy organizations. This is a small collection of his correspondence.
1.25 linear feet
Smedley, Frederick C.
Provenance
Donated to the Archives in 1999 by Dr. Herb Janick.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Frederic Smedley was born in New York City on June 4, 1906. In 1926, he graduated from Columbia College with a B.A. in economics, law, and history, and in 1928 from Columbia Law School with a LLB. He worked for the New York law firm of Duncan Mount for a brief period of time, and then became a research assistant to Prof. Philip C. Jessup of the Department of Public Law and Jurisprudence at Columbia. During this time he pursued graduate studies in the field of Public Law.
Shortly after marrying Naomi Coe, he and his wife moved to Waterbury, Connecticut, where he became a member of the Connecticut Bar in 1932 and reentered the practice of law. He was active in many liberal and progressive movements in the state, particularly the Connecticut Merit System.
In 1938 Smedley joined the Waterbury Local of the Socialist Party and became an active member. He ran for Comptroller, on the Socialist platform, in the municipal election of 1939. The Socialist Party's platform emphasized the belief that government should represent all the people and not be an instrument of special privilege. In 1948 he was the Socialist Party candidate for U.S. Senator from Connecticut.
Smedley was also counsel for the Waterbury Housing Authority, member of the National Lawyers Guild, Connecticut State and local Bar Associations, a member and officer of Liberty Lodge of Masons, Vice president of the University Club of Waterbury, counsel for the Waterbury Brass Workers Union, and Co-Operative Consumers of Waterbury, Inc.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of this collection contains correspondence related to Smedley's affiliation with the Socialist Party and his efforts toward civic and economic reform.
Frederic Smedley's personal correspondence files contain letters seeking employment with various law firms and government agencies, and letters of recommendation by faculty of Columbia University, School of Law, and congratulatory letters to Smedley upon passing the Connecticut Bar, business correspondence, and personal letters to his parents and relatives regarding family matters.
Smedley was a member of the Waterbury Chapter of The Citizens Good Government Association. His files contain drafts and correspondence concerning a proposed revision to the Waterbury Charter and Administrative Code that was to be placed on the ballot in the 1939 election.
Smedley was the Vice President of the Connecticut Merit System Association and a member of the committee drafting the proposed amendments to the Connecticut Merit System Law that would ensure fair and equitable treatment of all civil service employees in the state against political and personally motivated employment, promotion or dismissal. His files contain correspondence, minutes, newsletters, and proposed legislation.
Smedley's activities with the Connecticut Council of International Relations, which was an association of various state groups interested in developing public opinion on international affairs, included speaking engagements to various groups and organizations on the possibilities of a better world economic order. Correspondence concerning this subject can be found in his Personal and Socialist Party correspondence files.
The Keep American Out of War Congress files contain radio speeches, minutes of meetings, summary of the 1939 Atlantic City Conference, KAOW Congress Stamps, and newsletters.
Information concerning Smedley's activities in the Socialist Party includes the Socialist Party Platform for the 1939 municipal election in Waterbury, speeches, voting records of congressional members on international issues, and statistical analysis of the voting records on peace issues of the Connecticut delegation to Congress. These files also contain information about the Neutrality Bill that was before congress prior to World War II. Copies of Joint Resolutions regarding wartime activities such as the export of arms and ammunitions, extension of credits and issuance of foreign loans, and issuance of passports to American citizens are included.
Smedley was also active in the Waterbury Council for Peace Action (W.C.P.A.) and began to speak to organizations on disarmament and world peace.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Inventory
Related Material
Mooney-Billings Case Collection
John Mihelic Collection
Citizens for Good Government Association.; Connecticut Merit System Association.; Connecticut Peace Conference.; Keep America Out of War Congress - Mass., Washington D.C.; Kitchelt, Florence, 1874-1961; Labor Party of Connecticut.; League of Nations Association, Inc.; National Council for Prevention of War.; National Peace Conference; Smedley, Frederick C.; Socialist Party of Connecticut; Socialist Party of the U. S. A., Labor Party of Connecticut; Waterbury Council for Peace Action.; Correspondence.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Labor Movement.; Publications.; Socialists.; Waterbury (Conn.)
- Inventory
  - Correspondence (Personal), 1930-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1-18)
  - Citizens Good Government Association (Woodbury Chapter), 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association; Budget, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association; Correspondence, 1936-1941 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association; Correspondence (State), 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association; Legal Committee, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association; Minutes and Newsletters, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association; Proposed Legislation, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 28-31)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association; First Report of the State Civil Service Commission, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Connecticut Merit System Association; State Civil Service Commission (other states), 1929-1936 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Keep America Out of War Congress, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
  - Socialist Party Campaign Committee, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
  - Campaign (Labor), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 40-44)
  - Correspondence (Neutrality), 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
  - International, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Local Politics, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Peace Bond Campaign, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Speeches/Press Releases, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Waterbury Council for Peace Action; Correspondence, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - National Group Contacts, 1933-1943 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
  - Publicity, 1934-1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)